A Guide to the Lupton Family Papers, 1745-1895
Virginia Historical Society
Virginia Historical Society
Lupton Family Papers, 1745-1895
Virginia Historical Society
Mss1 L9747a FA2
1,400 (ca.) items.
Correspondence, accounts, land records, Society of Friends (Hopewell Meeting) records, miscellany and estate materials of David Lupton (1757-1822) of Apple Pie Ridge, Frederick County, Va. Also include correspondence, accounts,mercantile records and estate materials of Nathan Lupton (of Winchester, Va.). Also, include correspondence, accounts, bonds, Civil War materials and miscellany of Jonah H. Lupton (of Frederick County, Va.). Also, include letters, account books, accounts, bonds, agricultural records, saw mill records, patent materials and miscellany of Joel Lupton (of Apple Pie Ridge, Frederick County, Va.). Also, include letters, accounts, student notebook, literary club records, fam materials of David P. Lupton (of Springdale," Frederick County, Va.). Also, include materials of Mary Walker (Lupton) Irish, David Lupton (1786- 1814), Edward Walker Lupton, Hugh Sidwell Lupton, Isaac Lupton, Joseph Lupton (1718-1791), Joseph Lupton (1781-1825), and Lewis Lupton.
Administrative Information
Access
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift/purchase of Thornton Tayloe Perry, III, Washington, D.C., and Mrs. Barclay K. Read, McLean, Virginia, in 1984. Accessioned 20 June 1986.
Custodial History
Formerly a part of the collections of Thornton Tayloe Perry II of Charles Town, West Virginia.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Lupton family settled along Apple Pie Ridge near Winchester in Frederick County, Va., during the colonial period. Represented are farmer and landowner Joseph Lupton (1718-1791); his son, farmer, millwright and Quaker leader David Lupton (1757-1822); David's sons Joseph (1781-1825); David (1786-1814), a merchant in Alexandria, Va.; Nathan (1792?-1843), a merchant in Winchester, Va.; Jonah H. (1795-1870), farmer and horsebreeder; and Joel Lupton (1804-1883), farmer, millwright and manufacturer; and Jonah's son David P. Lupton (1846-1918) of "Springdale," Frederick County.
Scope and Content Information
Joseph Lupton (1718-1791) settled a large tract near Bobb's March in Frederick County and became a major landowner. His land records in this collection, covering the period 1759-1800, trace the title to a number of tracts in the county obtained from various parties. Joseph's son David Lupton (1757-1822) established the Quaker or Apple Pie Ridge branch of the family in Frederick County. He was a prominent farmer, millwright and Quaker leader. His correspondence, 1795-1822, largely focuses on family, fellow Quakers and on land dealings in Ohio. Among the more frequent or prominent correspondents are James Chenoweth (bearing a design for the internal mechanism of a grist mill); Philadelphia merchant and Quaker leader Samuel Rowland Fisher; Phineas Janney, an Alexandria merchant and Lupton's son-in-law; David Lupton (1786-1814), also a merchant in Alexandria; and Joseph Steer, a millwright and Quaker kinsman at Millgrove, Ohio.
David Lupton's accounts, 1810-1822, include records of funds collected as agent for Samuel and Miers Fisher of Philadelphia, Pa. His land records (Box 2) trace title to tracts in Frederick and Hampshire counties and lots in Winchester, Va., and consist of deeds, plats, grants, etc. The Hampshire County (now W. Va.) materials primarily consist of records, 1789-1821, from the lawsuit of Lupton v. Azariah Pugh in the Virginia Superior Court of Law for the county, concerning lands of Jesse Pugh and containing articles of separation, 1808, of Jesse Pugh and Elizabeth (Gray) Pugh.
As a member of Hopewell Meeting of the Society of Friends, David Lupton and his son Jonah H. Lupton recorded marriage certificates in the official record books. His papers contain a number of original marriage certificates, 1787-1833, signed by bridge and groom and witnessed by family members, guests, and members of the meeting. Included is a certificate for the marriage of David Lupton (1786-1814) and Ann McPherson at Hopewell in 1809.
David Lupton collected materials, 1758-1815, concerning the estate of Isaac Hollingsworth, father of Lupton's first wife, Mary (1758-1814). The materials concern land in Winchester, Va., and include the will of Hollingsworth written in Loudoun County, Va., in 1758. Materials, 1813-1823, of the estate of Thomas McClun, father of Lutpon's second wife, Rachel (b. 1773), include an inventory, will of Isaac Neil written in Frederick County, conditions for renting a plantation, a power of attorney to Nathan Lupton, an agreement and receipts. David Lupton served as an administrator of the estate of Henry Wells, a free black also known as "Black Harry" or "Free Harry." The materials contain an appraisal, account of the estate sale and general receipts.
Miscellany of David Lupton illustrates his importance as a community leader. This includes an affidavit of John Mason of Anacostia Island, D.C., 1812; notes on a packing press; an agreement concerning Lupton's arbitration of a dispute; a subscription to the literary work of educator Aquila Massey Bolton; a will of Nicholas Scarff written in Frederick County, 1815; and birth and death records of family members.
David Lupton's sons, Joseph, Nathan and Joel, served as executors of his estate. Materials, 1823-1851, include correspondence, bonds and accounts (including accounts with tenants and agents); an inventory and appraisal; notice (broadside) and account of the estate sale; deeds and other real property records, including the rental of a mill; an agreement of the heirs; and records of litigation, especially the lawsuit of Asa H. Hoge (administrator of Rebecca (Lupton) Hoge) et al v. Nathan Lupton in the Virginia Circuit Superior Court for Law and Chancery for Frederick County, which includes the estates of Issac and Joseph Lupton.
A few items exist in this collection for Joseph Lupton (1781-1825), David Lupton's eldest son. These include a trust agreement, 1817, miscellany, and an agreement and accounts of the estate, 1829. Lupton's son David (1786-1814) settled in Alexandria, Va., as a merchant. Records, 1814-1840, of his estate include a will written in 1814, materials in Ann (McPherson) Lupton v. Phinas Janney (including correspondence of lawyer Thomas Semmes with John McPherson Lupton), accounts and protested bonds of Abijah Janney & Co. Of Alexandria (also concerning John McPherson & Co. Of Alexandria); and letters and accounts, 1818- 1823, of Ann (McPherson) Lupton.
Nathan Lupton (1792?-1843), fourth son of David Lupton, worked as a merchant in Winchester, Va. His correspondence (Box 4), 1815-1843, is especially heavy for the years 1842-1843 and centers on the sale of flour, wheat and pig iron. There is much correspondence with Baltimore merchants and with George Franklin Hupp, proprietor of Columbia Furnace in Shenandoah County, and Joseph S. Machir, a Strasburg merchant. Nathan Lupton's account book, 1828, concerns farm labor, construction costs and the estates of David Lupton (1757-1822), Joseph Lupton (1781-1825) and Isaac Lupton. His accounts, 1829-1835, 1842-1843, detail a mixture of personal and business concerns.
As a merchant, Lupton kept receipts for the sale and shipment of wheat and flour and store orders for merchandise, 1842-1843. Receipts, 1842-1843, for the transportation of pig and bloom iron from Columbia Furnace by R. W. Ashton for George Franklin Hupp are largely directed to John Mason of Georgetown, D.C. Miscellany includes a trusteeship for John McPherson and Son of Alexandria in 1818. Estate materials consist of an inventory, appraisals, receipts and bonds.
Nathan's brother Jonal H. Lupton (7195-1870) was a Frederick County farmer and horse-breeder. His few items of correspondence, 1823-1861, primarily consist of family letters, but there are some letters from Quaker educator and historian Samuel McPherson Janney at Springdale Boarding School in Loudoun County (see also accounts, 1855). Jonah Lupton's bonds include a number executed by Phineas Janney as president of the Bank of the Potomac in Alexandria, D.C. (now Va.), 1843-1846.
A number of items relate to the family of Martha Ann Sidwell, Jonah Lupton's first wife. These include an epitaph for Martha Ann Sidwell (1792-1795); will of Richard Sidwell probated in Frederick County, 1805; unexecuted deed for land of Richard Sidwell; letters, 1818-1836, written to Martha Ann (Sidwell) Lupton and her commonplace book, 1813-1814, consisting primarily of lines of verse. Jonah H. Lupton's Civil Ware materials include a copy of a petition, 1863, of the loyal citizens of Winchester and Frederick County to Abraham Lincoln in behalf of General Robert Huston Milroy (signed by Jonah and Joel Lupton and 63 others); an account of property taken in 1861; passes; a certificate of loyalty, permit, order and requisition. Lupton's miscellany includes Society of Friends materials, 1829-1869, and two items of his second wife, Lydia (Walker) Lupton.
Joel Lupton (1804-1883) also lived along Apple Pie Ridge, where he pursued a busy career as farmer, millwright and manufacturer. Lupton received letters, 1823-1878, from a number of different inventors and agents who were seeking to sell and distribute their versions of early threshing machines. Among these were Dr. Chester Clark of Philadelphia and Hazard Knowles of Washington, D.C. Lupton also took great interest in sawmill operation, as well as entering a business partnership with Henry Lowe of Baltimore in the paper manufacturing firm of Lavender, Lowe and Lupton.
The account book, 1846-1866, of Joel Lupton concerns timber harvesting and sawmill operation with his brother Lewis. They had contracted to supply the Winchester and Potomac Railroad Company with their lumber needs. The book also bears accounts with Ridge Meeting of the Society of Friends in Frederick County (final page) and accounts of an unidentified Winchester merchant, 1815-1832 (the volume is filed oversize following Box 6).
His accounts, 1823-1883, heaviest in the 1830s-1840s, indicate Joel Lupton invested significantly in the Winchester and Potomac Railroad, like his brothers. Agricultural records consist of railroad receipts for the shipment of hay, flour inspection certificates, receipts for the sale of wheat, and rates and regulations on the Winchester and Potmac Railroad. Agreements and deeds concerning land in Frederick and Hampshire counties, 1829-1847, largely concern mills.
A number of items chronicle Joel Lupton's dealings with inventors or their agents (Box 7). These include Dr. Chester Clark and Pierson Reading (for improvements on threshing machines) and George C. Cochran (as an agent of manufacturers of a sausage meat cutter). Joel Lupton's miscellany contains records of sawmill operations, 1845-1851 (including an unexecuted agreement with the Winchester and Potomac Railroad Company); materials concerning the partnership of Lavender, Lowe, and Lupton; and records of a trusteeship by Henry Moore Brent.
David P. Lupton (1846-1918), a son of Jonah H. Lupton, lived at "Springdale" in Frederick County. Letters, 1888-1895, written to this farmer are mostly from kinsmen. A student notebook, 1869, concerns the principles of surveying. Lupton and his younger sister, Rebecca Jane (Lupton) Broomell (1848-1924), belonged to a local literary club known as "The Sociable." Some records of this group that survive here are minutes (kept by their cousin Maria C. Lupton as secretary) and criticisms of meetings, 1873-1876, as well as copies of several handwritten numbers of a literary "magazine" edited by David and Rebecca Lupton, "The Social Evening," a work "Devoted to Literature, Humor, etc." (1874-1882). There is also one number of a similar volume edited by David P. Lupton called "The White Star: Devoted to Literary, Social and Moral Advancement" (1887).
Farm materials of David P. Lupton consist of a deed for land, 1873; a certificate awarded by the Mutual Farmers' Club of Frederick County; notes and reports, 1874, to the Mutual Farmers' Club on dairy farming, animal husbandry and corn crops; an agreement, 1890; and broadsides.
The last portion of the collection consists of a few items each for David Lupton'sa sons Isaac and Lewis Lupton; John M. Lupton and Co. Of Winchester, Va. (Operated by John McPherson Lupton, son of David Lupton (1786-1814)); and children of Jonah H. Lupton: Edward Walker Lupton, Hugh Sidwell Lupton and Mary Walker (Lupton) Irish.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials arranged into series according to primary creator.
Organization
The ten series are further subdivided by document type and organized chronologically.
Index Terms
Agriculture -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century.; Apple Pie Ridge (Frederick County, Va.) -- History.; Family -- Virginia -- Social life and customs.; Farm life -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century.; Frederick County (Va.) -- Economic conditions -- 19th century.; Hopewell Monthly Meeting (Society of Friends); Irish, Mary Walker Lupton.; Lupton, David, 1757-1822.; Lupton, David, 1786-1814.; Lupton, David P., 1846-1918.; Lupton, Edward Walker.; Lupton family.; Lupton, Hugh Sidwell.; Lupton, Isaac.; Lupton, Joel, 1804-1883.; Lupton, Jonah H., 1795-1870.; Lupton, Joseph, 1718-1791.; Lupton, Joseph, 1781-1825.; Lupton, Lewis.; Lupton, Nathan, 1792?-1843.; Merchants -- Virginia -- Frederick County -- History -- 19th century.; Mills and mill-work -- Virginia -- Frederick County -- History -- 19th century.; Saw-mills -- Virginia -- Frederick County -- History -- 19th century.; Society of Friends -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century.; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Winchester (Va.) -- History -- 19th century.
Contents List
- Joseph Lupton (1718-1791), Frederick County, Va. 1759-1800 (Box 1)
  Land records.
- David Lupton (1757-1822), Apple Pie Ridge, Frederick County, Va.
  - Correspondence, 1757-1822 (Box 1 (cont.))
  - Accounts, 1810-1822 (Box 1 (cont.))
  - Land records, 1745-1821 (Box 2)
  - Quaker marriage certificates (Box 2 (cont.))
  - Estates of Isaac Hollingsworth, Thomas McClun, and Henry Wells. (Box 2 (cont.))
  - Miscellany (Box 2 (cont.))
  - Estate, 1823-1851 (Box 3)
- Joseph Lupton (1781-1825), Frederick County, Va. (Box 3 (cont.))
  Agreements, miscellany, estate accounts.
- David Lupton (1786-1814), Alexandria, Va. (Box 3 (cont.))
  Estate materials; Ann (McPherson) Lupton materials.
- Nathan Lupton (1792?-1843), Winchester, Va. 1815-1843
  - Correspondence, 1815-1843 (Box 4)
  - Financial papers. (Box 4 (cont.))
    Account books, loose accounts and bonds, wheat and flour receipts, store orders, 1843; iron trade.
  - Miscellany and estate. (Box 4 cont.))
- Jonah H. Lupton (1795-1870), Frederick County, Va. 1823-1861
  - Correspondence, 1823-1861 (Box 5)
  - Financial materials. (Box 5 (cont.))
  - Sidwell family materials. (Box 5 (cont.))
  - Civil War materials. (Box 5 (cont.))
  - Miscellany. (Box 5 (cont.))
- Joel Lupton (1804-1883), Apple Pie Ridge, Frederick County, Va. 1823-1883
  - Letters, 1823-1878 (Box 5 (cont.)-6)
  - Account book, loose accounts, and bonds. 1823-1883 (Box 7)
  - Agricultural materials and land records, patent materials, and miscellany. (Box 7 (cont.))
- David P. Lupton (1846-1918), "Springdale," Frederick County, Va. 1874-1894
- Miscellaneous family materials.
  T
  - Letters, 1888-1895 (Box 8)
  - Accounts and bonds, 1874-1894 (Box 8 (cont.))
  - School and club materials; miscellany. (Box 8 (cont.))
- General Miscelleous family materials.
  - Isaac Lupton. (Box 9)
  - Lewis Lupton. (Box 9 (cont.))
  - John McPherson Lupton. (Box 9 (cont.))
  - Edward Walker Lupton. (Box 9 (cont.))
  - Hugh Sidwell Lupton. (Box 9 (cont.))
  - Mary Walker (Lupton) Irish. (Box 9 (cont.))
- General miscellany. (Box 9 (cont.))
  Frederick County land records; unclassified miscellany.